A Guide to the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) FA079
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Photographs, 1946-1968, n.d.; 19.0 Boxes
  - Venezuela
    - CBR, Guarico, Agriculture (Box 10, Folder 190)
      1. This Guarico farmer is clearing the sperture into the "bacaquero" (ant hill) in preparation for filling it with the chlorodane spray. Such any hills are found frequently in corn fields near Calabozo. 2. This Guarico farmer applies the spray directly into the opening of the ant hill, thereby effectively eliminating a large number of the destructive red ants which infest his corn field near Calabozo. 3. This Guarico farmer applies the spray directly into the opening of the ant hill, thereby effectively eliminating a large number of the destructive red ants which infest his corn field near Calabozo. 4. A Ministry of Agriculture demonstrator sets out for a Guarico corn field with a can of chlorodane spray packed on his back. His job is to show farmers of the Calabozo area in Guarico how to spray the bachacos (red ants) which attack their crops. 5. This farmer had bought a supply if insecticide from the Guarico office of Banco Agricola and Pecuaria in Calabozo and is paying for his purchase. 6. Farmers attending the course in operation of equipment offered by CBR technicians in Guarico learn to care for the expensive machines they handle. 7. This Guarico farmer has drenched the "bachaqueros" (ant hills) inhabited by the destructive VE red antsnow he is dousing the "roads" which they have built from the ant hills to the corn plants. 8. The famous VE bachacos (red ants) destroyed one-tenth of this corn crop on a farm near Calabozo in Guarico. 9. A pair of bachacos are having themselves a feast on this corn leaf in a field near Calabozo. 10. Here the camera of Paul Meyn has penetrated the privacy of a bachaco road, leading from the any hill to the corn field on a farm near Calabozo, state of Guarico. 12. Those VE bachacos have a formidable appetite. Look at what they have done to a tree trunk on a farm near Calabozo, Guarico. 13. This is the bachaquero where a large community of the marauding red ants of Guarico have established headquarters. This shot was taken on a farm near Calabozo. This indicates just how large the bachaqueros really are. The photo was taken on a farm near Calabozo. 14. Here is a queen bachaco leaving the nest to celebrate her nuptials. This photo was taken on a farm near Calabozo. 15. This shows just how large the bachaco queen is. She still had her wings which she will lose shortly after breeding. The photo was taken on a farm near Calabozo. 16. Here is a male bachaco of the class dedicated to breeding. The photo was taken on a farm near Calabozo. 17. Here is a male breeder and two "soldier" bachacos. The former is a dilettante, and the latter do the work. 18. Here is a sampling of the entire bachacos family: in the foreground is an unbred queen - she still has her wingsbehind her is her more experiences, wingless sisterthe second winged apt is the breeding malebeside him is a dead, wingless malethe largest ant is a "soldier", and the two small ants are "slaves". The photo was taken on a farm near Calabozo, Guarico. 19. The regional branches of Banco Agricola y Pecuaria (Farmers and Stockmen's Bank) stock insecticides for exterminating the bachaco. Here an agent is discussing the product with a prospective buyer in Calabozo. 20. This farmer has bought a supply of insecticide from the Guarico office of Banco Agricola y Pecuaria in Calabozo and is paying for his purchase. 21. The chlorodane liquid is shot directly into the "bachaquero", headquarters of a marauding band of red ants which attack the corn fields in the region of Calabozo. 22. In addition to spraying directly into the opening of the ant hill, it was recommended to the farmers that they also spray the area around each "bachaquero", as the farmer is shown doing here in his corn field near Calabozo. 23. Another chlorodane bath is given the bachacos which infest the corn fields near Calabozo. 24. Guarico farm worker sign up for the course in the operation of farm equipment at the office of the Ministry of Agriculture veterinarian in Calabozo. 25. The central shop of the tractor-training course established at Galpon in Guarico is equipped with a full set of mechanics tools in the event a piece of training equipment needs repair. CBR technicians are assisting the Ministry of Agriculture in offering the course. 26. Maintenance of the machinery is a primary concern of students attending the course in operation of farm equipment offered by CBR technicians in Guarico. 27. This student is taking a hose to the disk attachment for his tractor. Part of the course in operation of farm equipment offered by CBR technicians in the state of Guarico consists in learning systematic methods for care and maintenance of the machinery. 28. This "tractorista" is checking the motor of his vehicle before giving it a practice run on the field at Galpon, Guarica. 29. CBR technicians and students look on while one budding "tractorista" takes his tuen for a trial operation of the machine. The course was offered at Galpon in Guarico. 30. Dr. Sanchez Medina, Director of Agriculture for the Ministry of Agriculture (right) and Capt. Navarro, representative of the state of Guarico, officiate at the presentation of diplomas to the first class of tractor operators to be graduate from the Agricultural Training Center operated by CBR technicians for the Ministry. 31. Howard Law, CBR technician, delivers a diploma to one of the first group to complete the course in this operation of farm machinery offered at Galpon in Guarico. 32. On the truck bed are officials of the Ministry of Agriculture, Guarico government representatives and CBR technicians, all participants in the presentation of diplomas to the first group of farmers to complete the course offered in the operation of farm equipment at Galpon, Guarico. 33. This is a field in the state of Guarico during the rainy season. In the dry season, this same field is parched and cracked. To eliminate such extremes, the VE government is building the giant Guarico dam. 34. This is a typical field near Calabozo. The big Guarico River dam, which the VE government now is constructing will provide a reservoir for collecting such water as run-off and will store it until the subsequent dry season, when such fields as the one shown become parched and cracked from lack of moisture. 35. This is a Guarico rice field. 36. Heavy rains have caused extensive erosion in this Guarico field. 37. This corn field has suffered greatly from an infestation of the army worm. 38. Considerable stirring is necessary to mix the chlorodane powder with water to be used as a spray against the ravenous bachacos which infest the corn fields of Guarico. 39. If a mechanical sprayer is unobtainable, the Guarico farmer can resort to a good-sized tin can with holes punched in the bottom. Such an improvised sprayer is demonstrated by this farmer in ridding his corn field near Calabozo of the destructive "bachacos". 40. Here the farmer is preparing chlorodane mixture for spraying his field against the bachaco. The photo was taken at a farm home near Calabozo in Guarico. 41. This Guarico farmer now has a diploma which states that he is qualified to operate a tractor and the various attachments used with it. He was among the first group to complete the farm equipment operation course offered by CBR technicians for the Ministry of Agriculture. 42. Children help themselves at the Yagua community center milk station. Volunteer mothers prepare the food, donated by the state, for serving fifty children daily.
    - CBR, Guarico, Western Guarico Report (Box 10, Folder 191)
      43. - 94. No caption.
    - CBR, Lara/Margarita, Agriculture (Box 10, Folder 192)
      1. The cut forage is poured into the newly-completed trench on the Hacienda Bocaro near Arenales, in Lara. 2. Work is underway on a trench silo designed to store the surplus rainy season forage, so that cattle of the state of Lara may be assured of a cheap, year-round food supply, and the milk production of the area, which fluctuated greatly from season to season, may be stabilized. 3. Following up the tractor, which spread and tamped the forage dumped into the new trench silo at the hacienda Bocaro in Lara, these two obreros with pitchforks complete the leveling process. 4. Laborers on the Bocaro Hacienda in Lara are cutting forage to fill the trench silo constructed by CBR as a measure toward a year-round food supply for cattle in this key dairy region. 5. No caption. 6. A bulldozer goes to work for CBR building the first text trench silo at the dairy farm "El Papelon" in the Torres district of Lara. 7. Livestock specialist, Dr. Edguardo Monolfu, in boots, is supervising the lining of a trench silo constructed on the Hacienda Bocaro at Arenales in Lara. 8. A tractor tamps the dry season silage dumped into the trench silo, constructed by CBR on the Hacienda Bocaro near Arenales, state of Lara, as a measure toward a year - round food supply for cattle of the region and stabilization of the region's greatly fluctuating milk production. 9. CBR's home gardening program is making an important contribution to the balancing of diets of farm families. 10. Following up the tractor, which speard and tamped the forage dumped into the new trench silo at the Hacienda Bocaro in Lara, these two obreros with pitchforks complete the leveling process. 11. No caption. 12. This pair of oxen at the Hacienda Bocaro near Arenales, Lara, is hauling forage to be chopped for storing in the newly constructed trench silo. 13. This steer appears to be well satisfied with the meal of ensilage served him from the trench silo constructed by CBR at Haciendo Bocaro. 14. Walls of inexpensive trench silos require a certain slant. Workmen are careful to see that the test project at "el Papelon" dairy farm in Lara is prepared properly. 15. This grader raises a lot of dust as it planes down the trench silo built at "El Papelon" dairy farm in Lara as a demonstration of how to beat the seasonal food shortage which causes sharp fluctuation in milk production of that key area. 16. Sudan grass grows high during the rainy season in the Torres district of Lara, and diary production is double that of the preceding dry season. CBR hopes to help stabilize the situation by storing some of this verdant forage in trench silos. 17. Cows munch forage in the modern stable at the "el Papelon" dairy in the Torres district of Lara, one of VE's key dairy-producing regions. 18. This is where dairy farm "el Papelon" in the Torres district of Lara where CBR conducted its first trench silo demonstration for the benefit of cattlemen who are faced with a feed shortage during the dry season when the grass withers and disappears. 19. Erosion, one of VE's worst plagues, has rutted this hillside in Lara. 20. A trench silo, constructed by CBR at Hacienda Boacro near Arenales, is lined with waterproof material. 21. A bulldozer goes to work for CBR building the first test trench silo at the dairy farm "el Papelon" in the Torres district of Lara. 22. Farmers of the area, agricultural experts and government officials were among the many visitors who flocked to the Bocaro Hacienda last January to watch the filling of the first trench silo in their area and the first many of them ever had seen. 23. CBR's assistant Director Fernando Rondon, left, and visitors to the Hacienda Bocaro, watch the "historic" filling of the first trench silo in the region, constructed near Arenales, Lara, heart of one of VE's chief dairy producing areas. 24. No caption.
    - CBR, Lara/Margarita, General (Box 11, Folder 193)
      25. - 48. No caption. 49. El Tocuyo after the earthquake of August 3, 1950. 50. No caption. 51. Radio broadcast. 52. Radio broadcast.
    - CBR, Lara/Margarita, Nutrition (Box 11, Folder 194)
      53. A milk station where children from two to five years old are served a free glass of milk daily was inaugurated last week at La Fuente, Margarita Island in the Community Center opened there this spring by CBR.
    - CBR, Merida, Farm-to-Market Road (Box 11, Folder 195)
      1. Road in Merida is one of the 28 farm-to-market road projects pioneered by CBR in 11 Venezuelan states. 2. CBR-engineered farm-to-market roads wind through foothills in Merida. 3. CBR-engineered farm-to-market roads wind through foothills in Merida.
    - CBR, Peribeca, Crafts (Box 11, Folder 196)
      1. Housewives come to CBR center at Peribeca for all afternoon sewing class each Thursday. 2. Small girls from Tachira learn elementary sewing at CBR community center at Peribeca.
    - CBR, Tachira, Agriculture (Box 11, Folder 197)
      1. Plots sown laterally to minimize erosion, on Tachira hillsides show the growing acceptance of CBR advice. 2. Great gulches have been dug by erosion in the Libertad area of the Andean State of Tachira. CBR programs of soil conservation are badly needed. 3. CBR technician Fernando Rodon gives pointers to a worker on the Juan Domador farm in the EL Porvenir community of the Sta. of Tachira concerning the care of tomatoes, one of Domador's principal crops. The worker at Rondon's suggestion is adding an extra brace to support the heavy plants. 4. CBR supervised credit in the Peribeca area of the Sta. of Tachira has facilitated this carefully sown onion crop, divided by a drainage ditch. 5. On the upland farm of Antonio M. Cardenas of the La Laja community in Tachira, CBR supervised credit has helped with the production of a good crop of peas. 6. American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) March, 1950-CBR technician directs maintenance work on sugar-cane machinery. 7. This Andean farmer applies new practices learned at CBR demonstrations to his fields on the slopes of Libertad Village. Technicians visit farmers regularly to inspect crops and give follow-up instruction and supervision. 8. Andean farmer utilizes new insecticide sprayer purchased through CBR supervised credit on cabbage fields. Venezuela, March 1950. 9. Sr. Alcidez Ramirez, recipient of CBR supervised credit in El Paramo, State of Tachira, grows corn and keeps bees. 10. Bulldozer pushes through corn field to open up way from farming area to marketing centers, under CBR's rural road construction program. These rural roads are of great economic importance to farmers who have been forced to take produce to market over mule trails. 11. Laborers spray tomato plants to control insect pests, according to CBR prescription, on the hillside farm of Juan Domador in the El Porvenir vicinity in the Andean State of Tachira. 12. Pedro Celestino received CBR supervised credit on the strength of his flourishing tobacco crop at Peribeca in the State of Tachira. 13. US Forest Service Engineer, Edward Morris, and machine mechanic Gordon Privett point out trail over which produce is transported to market in rough Andes Mountain region in Western VE. 14. Sixteen ton bulldozers push through corn fields in Andes Mountain region in Western VE to open up gravel road which will help solve farm-to-market transportation. 15. Many farmers in the area bring their products to the Free Market in Tariba, Tachira, scene of early morning activity. 16. The hillside farm of Juan Domador in the Community of El Porvenir, State of Tachira, is planted half to garlic (foreground) and half to tomatoes. Laborers are working with the latter group. Domador is one of the farmers with whom CBR is working through supervised credit. 17. Fidel Contramaestre of Pueblito in the State of Tachira, a recipient of CBR supervised credit, has a mechanized sugar mill. Here his workers apply some manual labor to get the machine started. 18. A worker at the Fidel Contramaestre sugar mill in Pueblito stacks blocks of brown sugar for marketing. This product (papelon) is universally consumed throughout Venezuela. Contramaestre is a recipient of CBR supervised credit. 19. Leaves of tobacco are strung up to dry in a shed on the Pedro Celestino farm in Peribeca, Tachira. Celestino is a recipient of CBR supervised credit. 20. Pioneer Cardenas farmers are planting corn in an uncleared field. The territory just has been opened for cultivation. CBR technicians can show them how to clear the field and greatly augment their production. 21. Here, the pioneer Cardenas farmer has planted a haphazard mixture of corn and rice in his eagerness to get production under way. CBR agents can explain to the farmer why this practice is ineffective and what he can do to improve his yield. 22. Agent and "credit" - CBR's Fernando Rondon and coffee farmer Placido Mendez of the Pueblito community in Tachira - study the berry formation on a coffee plant. 23. CBR's Fernando Rondon inspects coffee berries with Placido Mendez on the latter's farm in the Pueblito vicinity of the State of Tachira. Mendez has received supervised credit on his coffee shop. 24. CBR agents have explained to Jose Cardenas that he must care for his onions while they are in storage. He is turning the onions to avoid their becoming damp and rotted. 25. Jose Cardena and his wife sort their onion crop, selecting the choice ones for seed and putting others in baskets for marketing. Cardenas, who farms in the Independencia vicinity, has received advice concerning seed selection by CBR agents with whom he is working through supervised credit. 26. Soil conservation through terracing is practiced successfully at Belandria, Tachira. 27. This view of Libertad community in Tachira vividly exposes the difference between eroded sections and those which have been subjected to contour planting. 28. This Capacho District Hillside in Tachira shows a patchwork of cultivation. CBR technicians are at work with farmers in this area, helping them with terracing problems and the selection of crops. 29. CBR supervised credit enabled Antonio M. Cardenas of La Laja in Tachira to build this sturdy modern poultry shed. 30. Poultry are penned securely on Antonio Cardenas' farm at La Laja in the Andean State of Tachira, thanks to suggestions he has received from CBR agents as means for straightening his flock and increasing his egg and meat yield. 31. Pedro Parra's cow takes salt from a cement container, built with funds scquired through CBR supervised credit. The Parra farm is in El Llanito community of Tachira. 32. Cows rest securely behind fences on the Tachira farm of Pedro Parra, recipient of CBR supervised credit. 33. Andean farmer utilizes new insecticide sprayer, purchased through CBR supervised credit on cabbage fields. 34. CBR technician makes regular visit to fields of Andean farmer cultivating under the supervised credit program. 35. Angel Maria Huerfano feeds sugar cane into a press. A CBR- supervised credit enabled him to replace the press's donkey power with a gas engine, increasing his yearly production, brown sugar loaves, by ten times. 36. Traffic is heavy the year round on new "farm-to-market" road constructed as a CBR experimental project last year in the VE Andes state, Tachira. The success of the low-cost road, which connects four farming communities, has resulted in a broad program with CBR technical supervision under which eleven additional states have entered contracts for the construction of a network of rural roads. 37. Erosion presents a serious problem in mountainous Tachira state. CBR technicians can show the farmer how to conserve his soil by terracing, contour planting, proper selection of crops and other scientific control methods. They are shown in the vicinity of Libertad. 38. A pioneer's pasture clearing in the newly-settled region of Cardenas reveals the VE's urgency to start farming. CBR hopes to help him and his neighbors. 39. Tachira onion growers pack their product by burro to market. These three have set out from the community of La Laja. 40. - 46. No caption.
    - CBR, Tachira, Crafts (Box 11, Folder 198)
      47. At the CBR Community Center in El Valle, State of Tachira, young girls learn handcrafts. Here they are intent upon some needlework. 48. Home management technician Miss Idea Reboyras, supervises fitting in sewing class at CBR center in Peribeca, Andes. 49. CBR home technicians lend a hand to local schools in the Andes, giving weekly sewing and gardening sessions in three schools in the area.
    - CBR, Tachira, Education (Box 11, Folder 199)
      50. Here is the provisional Puerto Nuevo School, "Casa Maria Miranda," built of cane poles and thatched. The town recently was settled in a pioneer section of Tachira.
    - CBR, Tachira, Farm-to-Market Road (Box 11, Folder 200)
      51. Edward E. Morris, US Forest Service engineer, who surveyed area and laid out route of new road. Mr. Morris is shown using a simple surveying instrument with which he maintained inclines at seven per cent maximum. 52. Edward E. Morris indicates route of present burro train to E. Gordon Privett, also of US Forest Service, who is supervising training and operations of Venezuela student tractor drivers building new road. 53. Showing character of fertile agriculture area serviced by new farm-to-market road in Tachira, near San Cristobal. 54. Tortuous path of burro trail, seen from elevation of clearing for new farm-to-market road near San Cristobal, Tachira. 55. Student tractorist working on fill to widen curve. At this high point, road makes sharpest turn of entire route. 56. Bulldozer powered by TD-18 heavy tractor clearing heavily wooded section for farm-to-market all duty road. 57. TD-18 tractor with bulldozer making fill at sharpest curve on farm-to-market road near San Cristobal. Roadway here is widened to accommodate passing vehicles. 58. TD-18 tractor at highest point of farm to market road under construction near San Cristobal, Tachira. 59. Youthful student driver uses TD-18 tractor with bulldozer to clear route of new farm-to-market road near San Cristobal. 60. Showing completed stretch of farm-to-market road. Gravel and rock from nearby riverbed form surface of road, which now accommodates heavy trucks and passenger buses. Month before, only burros carried cargoes to and from this point. 61. Completed section of farm-to-market road near San Cristobal, showing one of deep cuts made to maintain maximum inclination of seven per cent. 62. E. Gordon Privett with student tractor drivers. These young Venezuelans are first of corps of technicians who will carry through road building program in Tachira. 63. Motor patrol ditches stretch of rural road being constructed through 14 miles of rich cattle country in Portuguesa State under CBR farm to market road program in VE. 64. New rural road being constructed under CBR technical supervision connects isolated farming regions with main highway leading into market centers. 65. No caption.
    - CBR, Tachira, Gardening (Box 11, Folder 201)
      66. Women and children work in the demonstration garden at the CBR Community Center in Peribeca, Tachira.
    - CBR, Tachira, General (Box 11, Folder 202)